Drew Allbritten Papers
Drew Allbritten Papers
1969-2011
1995-2005
Allbritten, Drew William
9.5 linear ft
Drew Allbritten has been involved in education and government at the local, state, and national levels. In education, he served as a secondary and postsecondary teacher, counselor, and administrator. In government, he served in elected and appointed positions at the state and federal levels, respectively. Papers in the collection relate for the most part to his positions as Executive Director of the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (1991-1998), Executive Director of the Georgia Association of Educators (1998-2002), and Executive Director of the Council for Exceptional Children (2003-2005).
2477681
Biographical History
Drew Allbritten (b. 1947) is an American educator, administrator, consultant, policy expert and scholar in public administration and management.
Dr. Drew Allbritten has been an active leader in education and government at the local, state, and national levels for over thirty years. In education, he served as a secondary and postsecondary teacher, counselor, and administrator. In government, he served in elected and appointed positions at the state and federal levels, respectively. In addition to effectively managing associations, foundations, and political action committees at the state and national levels, Allbritten was a committed community leader and advocate as well as an active participant in workshops, conferences, symposia, advisory councils, and consultations.
Allbritten began his career as a middle school and high school mathematics and science teacher. He served as a college administrator and was a state representative in the Michigan legislature, executive director of the Iowa Association of Community College Trustees, and a presidential appointee for Intergovernmental Relations at the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development.
From 1991-1998 he was Executive Director of the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE). During his tenure he played an instrumental role in the development and implementation of the association's strategic plan and reorganization; orchestrated national public policy efforts that increased federal funding for adult learning by 35%; reduced AAACE spending by nearly 35% (saving nearly $800,000) and increased membership by 7% and publication subscribers by 8%.
From 1998-2002 he served as Executive Director of the Georgia Association of Educators, overseeing its restructuring and actively participating in political issues related to education in Georgia. In 2003, Allbritten became Executive Director of the Arlington, Virginia-based Council for Exceptional Children (CEC), a special education association dedicated to serving professionals, organizations, and parents of children with a variety of physical, mental, and emotional challenges.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Drew Allbritten Papers reflect Allbritten's interest in educational policy, consisting primarily of material relating to his positions as Executive Director of the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) (1991-1998), Executive Director of the Georgia Association of Educators (GAE) (1998-2002), and Executive Director of the Council for Exceptional Children (CEC) (2003-2005).
Biographical material consists of desk calendars with extensive annotations, clippings about Allbritten or in which he is quoted, personal journals covering 16 years, and miscellaneous material such as a family holiday letters, a handmade card, and an invitation to grandparents' day.
General, which contains material professional in nature but unrelated to the three organizations listed above, is divided into correspondence-subject files and memorabilia. Correspondence-subject files concern oganizations or programs with which Allbritten was involved, including American Federation of Teachers, Coalition of Lifelong Learning Organizations, Iowa Association of Community College Trustees, James Monroe Foundation, National Coalition for Technology in Education and Training (NCTET), National Education Association, National Middle School Association, and Virginia Business-Education Partnership Program. There are also four videotapes of various events. Memorabilia includes nametags, badges and photographs from several different education-related events.
Charles Drew University material relates to several projects undertaken for the private non-profit in Los Angeles, California, including planning for a network of local health clinics, four-year medical school planning committee, and the University's efforst to obtain the Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBU) and Predominantly Black Intitution (PBI) designations.
Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE) consists of material from Allbritten's tenure as Executive Director of the AAACE. This series includes Correspondence-subject files (COABE's grievances with AAACE, a mock trial in which AAACE was convicted of not serving its members, history and bylaws of COABE, conference planning handbooks, directories, job descriptions, newsletters, policy manuals, and miscellaneous correspondence internal to COABE as well as between AAACE leadership and COABE leadership); Conferences (planning and execution of COABE conferences from 1993 to 2001, including site selection, hotel and convention center bids, catering negotiations, calls for papers, and so on); Financial (reimbursement requests, financial reports); and Miscellany consisting primarily of Allbritten's handwritten notes on various topics. Due to the amount of internal COABE correspondence, it is possible that some at least of these files were not originally Allbritten's but rather came from someone at COABE.
Georgia Association of Educators (GAE) consists of material from Allbritten's tenure as Executive Director of GAE. This series includes Correspondence-subject files (alternative teacher preparation, GAE constitution and bylaws, various GAE staff and committees, other Georgia education organizations, state and national education legislation and policy, and notable individuals such as Governor Roy Barnes, Senator Zell Miller, and School Superintendent Linda Schrenko); Meetings (agenda, minutes, and Allbritten's own notes for GAE Board of Director, Executive Committee, and other meetings); Writings (articles, introductions, remarks, speeches, and notes, including Allbritten's notes for a speech given soon after the World Trade Center terrorist attacks on 11 Sep 2001); and Miscellany consisting primarily of Allbritten's handwritten notes on various topics.
Council for Exceptional Children (CEC) covers Allbritten's tenure as Executive Director of CEC. This series includes Corresp ondence-subject files (CEC directories, various CEC staff and committee meetings, other education organizations such as National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education and the Yes I Can! Foundation); Meetings (agenda, minutes, and Allbritten's own notes for CEC Board of Director and other meetings); Writings (articles, introductions, remarks, speeches, and notes); and Miscellany material consisting primarily of Allbritten's handwritten notes on various topics.
Arrangement of the Collection
Within each series material is arranged alphabetically by type or topic.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) Records.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Allbritten, Drew William.; Barnes, Roy.; Miller, Zell, 1932-; Schrenko, Linda.; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; Charles R. Drew University of Medicine and Science.; Coalition of Lifelong Learning Organizations.; Commission on Adult Basic Education (U.S.); Council for Exceptional Children.; Georgia Association of Educators.; Republican Party (Ga.); Adult education.; Adult education educators.; Continuing education.; Early childhood special education.; Special education.; Special education educators.; Georgia -- Teachers.; Agendas (administrative records); Calendars (documents); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Electronic mail.; Job applications.; Diaries.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Notes (documents); Photographs.; Videotapes.; Adult education teachers.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Drew Allbritten, 2002-2010.
Accruals
Additional material may be added at irregular intervals.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Address books, 2 items (Box 11)
  - Calendars, 1998-2005; 2007-2010; Allbritten's desk calendars with appointments and notes; 14 calendars (Box 9)
  - Clippings about (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 11)
  - Journals, 1989-2006 (Box 9)
  - Miscellany, 1989; 1994,; 1996,; 1998-2004,; 2007 (Box 1)
- General
  - Correspondence subject files
    - American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) (Box 11)
      See also Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE) files.
    - American Federation of Teachers / National Education Association (AFT/NEA) merger, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Awards and affiliations, list of (Box 11)
    - Awards and recognitions, 1991; 1997-2004 (Box 1)
    - California Association for Safety and Education in Colon Hydrotherapy (Box 17)
    - Cambodia and Vietnam (Box 11)
    - Cassidy, Butch (Box 11)
    - China Business Unit (Box 17)
    - Coalition of Lifelong Learning Organizations (COLLO), 1995-1996; 2004-2005 (Box 1)
    - Congressional campaign, 1984 (Box 11)
    - Continuing education unit, 1993; 1997 (Box 1)
    - Dream-Maker Project, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "Drew at Santa Fe Jr. High 'Civil War'", Mar 1993; VHS tape (Box 10)
    - Glen Oaks Community College (Box 12)
    - "Good Morning America 7:35 am 'Older students in college' ", 3 Jan 1992; VHS tape (Box 10)
    - Helping Other People Excel (HOPE) (Box 12)
    - International Adult and Continuing Education Hall of Fame, 1998; 2003 (Box 1)
      See also General: Memorabilia: Photographs (Box 1)
    - Iowa Association of Community College Trustees (, 1990-1991; Allbritten was Executive Director, includes booklet for which he wrote the introduction (Box 1)
    - Iowa First Committee, 1990; Presidential visit to Des Moines, Iowa (Box 12)
    - James Monroe Foundation, 2002-2004; includes program from The Ambassador Briefing Series (Box 1)
    - Movie of the Mind (Box 12)
    - National Coalition for Technology in Education and Training (NCTET), 1993-1997; 2003-2005 (Box 1)
    - National Education Association
      - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
      - Job application, 2002 (Box 1)
      - Resignation letter, 2003 (Box 1)
      - Time sheets, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - National Education Goals Panel, 1992 (Box 1)
    - National Middle School Association, Allbritten served briefly as NMSA's Executive Director
      - Board of Trustees, Jun 2010-Jan 2011; meeting minutes and notes (Box 16)
      - Board of Trustees, miscellaneous documents and papers including reference manual (Box 16)
      - Branding exercise (Box 16)
      - Bullying Summit, Oct 2010 (Box 16)
      - Conference, Baltimore, Nov 2010 (Box 16)
      - Correspondence, Jul 2010-Jan 2011 (Box 16)
      - Executive Director's reports, articles, other writings (Box 17)
      - Financial and budget data (Box 17)
      - Notes, staff meetings, executive staff, all staff, miscellaneous; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Organization charts and notes (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous, includes Design Manual for Grand Rapids Junior College, 1978 (Box 17)
    - National Workforce Development Stakeholders Forum, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Reference and recommendation letters, from various individuals and organizations, re: Allbritten (Box 12)
    - Republican party, 1990-2005; Fayette County Republican Party, Georgia Republican Party, four issues of Reagan Alumni Newsletter 1990-1991, 1994 (Box 1)
      See also Awards and recognitions (Box 1); General: Memorabilia: Miscellany (Box 1)
    - "Safe Schools" US Department of Education teleconference, VHS tape (Box 10)
    - "Speakeasy" public speaking workshop, includes VHS tape, DA’s notes (Box 10)
    - Reagan, Ronald, 1983; letters of appreciation for his work for the Department of Housing and Urban Development (Box 12)
    - Thank-you letters, letters of appreciation and thanks to Allbritten (Box 12)
    - Transformation Strategies LLC, 2009 (Box 17)
    - U. S. Department of Education, 2005; application packet and letters, re: position of Undersecretary of Education; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - U. S. Department of Labor job application, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Unity Team, See American Federation of Teachers / National Education Association (AFT/NEA) merger (Box 1)
    - University of the South Pacific, 2010-2011; relating to application for position of Senior Fellow in Management and Public Administration (Box 1)
    - Watts Gang Task Force (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Virginia Business-Education Partnership Program, 1994-1995; 1997,; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Watts Gang Task Force (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Memorabilia
    - Business cards, Allbritten's (Box 13)
    - License plates (Box 17)
    - Photographs, 1991; 1994,; 1996,; 1998,; 2002,; 2003,; undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellany (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Poetry (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Miscellany (Box 1)
- Charles Drew University
  - Community Health Fair, 2007 (Box 13)
  - Community Investment Corp. (CIC), 2007 (Box 13)
  - Cuba trip, 2007; professional research trip sponsored by the University (Box 13)
  - Dymally, Mervyn (U.S. Representative from California), 2007-2008 (Box 13)
  - Executive summaries (Box 13)
  - Extreme Makeover, University Edition (Box 13)
  - Four-year medical school planning committee, 2007-2008; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Four-year medical school planning committee, 2007-2008 (Box 14)
  - Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCU) designation, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Network of Clinics, local health clinics (Box 14)
  - Policy and procedures manual (Box 14)
  - Predominantly Black Institution (PBI) designation (Box 15)
  - Project deliverables list (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 15)
- Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE)
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - Adult Basic Education, 1993-1999; COABE journal; includes annual reports (Box 1)
    - AAACE mock trial, 2000 (Box 1)
    - AAACE executive director job application, 1991 (Box 1)
      See also General: Awards and recognition (Box 1)
    - AAACE strategic plan, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Awards, 2000; See also Incentive grants and scholarships (Box 1) (Box 1)
    - Award nominees, 1998-1999; undated (Box 1)
    - Background/history of COABE, 1998; 2000,; undated (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, 1995; 1999-2001,; undated (Box 1)
    - California Council for Adult Education (CCAE), 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - COABE/AAACE retreat, 1995-1997 (Box 1)
    - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), 1999 (Box 1)
    - Conference planning handbook, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Directories and lists
      - AAACE, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
      - COABE, 1995-2001 (Box 1)
    - Endowment, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
    - Evaluation and surveys, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Grievance, undated; concerns COABE's grievances with AAACE
      See also Internal Revenue Service examiners’ concerns (Box 1); Memorandum of Understanding (MOU), AAACE-COABE (Box 1); May 1996 material in Miscellaneous correspondence: AAACE/COABE) (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
      - Allbritten's notes, 1996; undated (Box 1)
    - Handbook 2000, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Incentive grants and scholarships, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
    - Internal Revenue Service examiners’ concerns, 1997; undated (Box 1)
    - Job descriptions, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Laubach Literacy, 1996; 2000 (Box 1)
    - Legislative issues, 1994-2000; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Managing the Media", 1996 (Box 2)
    - Meeting minutes, 1993-2001; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Membership reports, 1995-1998; undated (Box 2)
    - Memorandum of Understanding (MOU), AAACE-COABE, 1997; undated (Box 2)
    - National Council of State Education Associations (NCSEA) handbook, 1998 (Box 2)
      See also Georgia Assoc. of Educators: National Council of State Education Associations (NCSEA) (Box 4)
    - Newsletters
      - AAACE, 1994-1999 (Box 2)
      - COABE, 1993; 1995-1999,; 2001 (Box 2)
      - Other (Box 2)
        See also General: Correspondence-subject files: Republican party (Box 1)
    - Papers and presentations, 1994; 1997,; undated (Box 2)
    - Planning committee, 1979; 1997-1998,; undated (Box 2)
    - Policies and procedures manual, AAACE, 1995; 1998 (Box 2)
    - Policies and procedures manual, COABE
      - 1989 edition (Box 2)
      - 1995 drafts (Box 2)
      - 1996 drafts (Box 2)
      - 1996 edition (Box 2)
      - 1997 drafts (Box 2)
      - Undated drafts (Box 2)
    - State profiles, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Site selection guidelines
      - Affiliate, 1995; undated (Box 2)
      - Convention bureau, undated (Box 2)
    - Smith Bucklin and Associates, 1993; 1996-1997,; undated (Box 2)
    - Strategic planning, See Planning committtee (Box 2)
    - Tennessee Association for Adult and Continuing Education, 1999-2000; undated (Box 2)
    - Websites
      - AAACE, 1998 (Box 2)
      - COABE, 1999-2000; undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - COABE, 1994-2001; undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
      - AAACE/COABE, 1996-2000; 3 folders (Box 2, 3)
  - Conferences
    - AAACE conferences, 1995; 1996,; 1998-2000 (Box 3)
    - COABE '93 (Box 3)
    - COABE '95 (Box 3)
    - COABE '96 (Box 3)
    - COABE '97 (Box 3)
    - COABE '98 (Box 3)
    - COABE '99 (Box 3)
    - COABE 2000 (Box 3)
    - COABE 2001 (Box 3)
    - Galaxy II, 1998-1999; includes material from Galaxy I (1969), presentation by Allbritten with notes (Box 3)
  - Financial
    - Check and reimbursement requests, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Financial reports, 1995-2001; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellany, consists mostly of Allbritten's handwritten notes on various topics (Box 3)
- Georgia Association of Educators (GAE)
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - 2002 student achievement survey (Box 3)
    - A+ Implementation Task Force, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Alternative teacher preparation, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Annual teacher conference, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Atlanta Journal-Constitution, 1999 (Box 3)
    - Barnes, Roy, 1999-2001 (Box 3)
      See also Education Coordinating Council (Box 3)
    - Board member orientation, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors policies, See also Representative Assembly / Board of Directors policies (Box 4) (Box 3)
    - Collective bargaining, 1998 (Box 3)
      See also UNISERV staff union membership survey (Box 5)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 2001 (Box 3)
    - "Conversations with CEOs", 1999 (Box 3)
    - Cracker Crumble, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Cribbs, Bob, 1998-2002; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Education Coordinating Council (ECC), 2001 (Box 3)
    - Educators Parternship Plan (EPP), See Collective bargaining (Box 3)
    - Elementary and Secondary Education Act (ESEA), 2002-2003; undated (Box 3)
    - Evaluation and surveys, 2000 (Box 3)
      See also 2002 student achievement survey (Box 3); UNISERV staff union membership survey (Box 5)
    - Executive director acceptance letter and contract, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Executive director search committee, 1998; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Fair dismissal policy, See Fayette County Board of Education (Box 3)
    - Fayette County Board of Education, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Financial reports, 2000; 2001; includes information on GAE, GFIE, GAE-FPE (Box 4)
    - Forum of Affiliate Leaders (FOAL), 2001 (Box 4)
    - GAE Fund for Public Education (GAE-FPE), 2002 (Box 4)
      See also Financial reports (Box 4)
    - GAE-Georgia Staff Organization (GSO) contract, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
    - Georgia Association of Colleges for Teacher Education (GACTE), 2001; includes notes from Allbritten’s presentation, "Impact of HB1187 on Quality Instruction and Student Learning Outcomes" (Box 4)
    - Georgia Association of Educational Leaders (GAEL), 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Georgia Foundation for the Improvement of Education (GFIE), 1999-2002 (Box 4)
    - Georgia Partnership for Excellence in Education (GPEE)
      - Board of Director’s handbook, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
      - Financial statements, 1988-2000; 2002 (Box 4)
      - Notes and correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Georgia State Board of Education, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
      See also Schrenko, Linda (Box 4)
    - Harold A. Dawson Management Company, 1998-2001 (Box 4)
    - Holt, Tyra, 1998-2002; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Honor Teacher Awards, See Atlanta Journal Constitution (Box 3)
    - Instruction and Professional Development (IPD), 1998-2003 (Box 4)
    - Job descriptions for staff, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Johnson, Essie, 1998-2000 (Box 4)
    - Kramer & Thomas, LLC, 1998-2002 (Box 4)
    - Leaders' Directory, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Leadership Development Academy, 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Legal counsel, See Kramer & Thomas, LLC (Box 4); Sloane, Pamela V. (Box 4)
    - Legislative conferences, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Lobby team, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - McGonigle, Michael, See Kramer & Thomas, LLC (Box 4)
    - Miller, Zell, 1998; 2000 (Box 4)
    - National Council of State Education Associations (NCSEA), 2001-2002 (Box 4)
      See also COABE: National Council of State Education Associations (NCSEA) handbook (Box 2)
    - Noble, Ralph, 2000-2002; 2 folders (Box 4)
      See also photo in Press kit (Box 4)
    - Noble Administration final report, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Orientation, See Board member orientation (Box 3)
    - Parham, Peggy, See Instruction and Professional Development (IPD) (Box 4) (Box 4)
    - Policies, See Representative Assembly / Board of Directors policies (Box 4) (Box 4)
    - Press kit, 2001-2002; includes photo of Ralph Noble (Box 4)
    - RA Today, 2001; 6 issues (Box 4)
    - Representative Assembly / Board of Directors policies, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Resignation letter, 2002 (Box 4)
    - SAT and income, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Schapiro and Associates, See Evaluations and surveys (Box 3)
    - School sales tax amendment, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Schrenko, Linda, 1998-2002 (Box 4)
    - September 11 terrorist attacks, See Writings (Box 6)
    - Senate Bill 163, undated; bill concerns teachers’ retirement (Box 4)
    - Sloane, Pamela V., 1998 (Box 4)
    - Smith, Evelyn, See Instruction and Professional Development (IPD) (Box 4)
    - Southeast Regional Partnership, 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Spelling bee, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
    - Spring convention, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Spring convention, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Staff meeting notes, 1998; 2001-2002 (Box 5)
    - Student GAE (SGAE), 2001-2002 (Box 5)
    - Thank-you and congratulation letters, 1998-2002 (Box 5)
    - Time sheets (Allbritten), 1998-2002 (Box 5)
    - UNISERV directors, 1998; 2000-2002,; undated (Box 5)
    - UNISERV staff union membership survey, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Update, Oct 2001 (Box 10)
    - "Update" vol. 33 (Aug 2000-Jul 2001), bound (Box 10)
    - "Using the Environment", 2002 (Box 5)
    - Williams, Merchuria, 1998; 2002 (Box 5)
    - Yancey, Grady, 1996; 1998 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - External, 1999-2002 (Box 5)
      - Internal, 1998-2002 (Box 5)
  - Meetings
    - 2001
      - Board of Directors, 19 Jan 2001 (Box 5)
      - Executive Committee, 19 Jan 2001; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Executive Committee, 24 Feb 2001 (Box 5)